<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>mathletix - basketball</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/basketball.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2026-02-17T10:20:00-10:00</updated><entry><title>NBA clutch statistics</title><link href="/nba-clutch-statistics.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2026-02-17T10:20:00-10:00</published><updated>2026-02-17T10:20:00-10:00</updated><author><name>casey durfee</name></author><id>tag:None,2026-02-17:/nba-clutch-statistics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RJmsNX9emKs" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="iiO – Rapture (Deep Dish Space Remix)" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/RJmsNX9emKs/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RJmsNX9emKs" target="_blank"&gt;iiO – Rapture (Deep Dish Space Remix)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notebook: &lt;a href="https://github.com/csdurfee/csdurfee.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/nba-clutch-stats.ipynb"&gt;https://github.com/csdurfee/csdurfee.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/nba-clutch-stats.ipynb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I'm discussing &lt;a href="https://www.nba.com/stats/teams/clutch-traditional?Season=2010-11"&gt;team clutch statistics from nba.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A basketball player who tends to make good plays in high-pressure situations is known as being "clutch". When the game …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RJmsNX9emKs" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="iiO – Rapture (Deep Dish Space Remix)" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/RJmsNX9emKs/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RJmsNX9emKs" target="_blank"&gt;iiO – Rapture (Deep Dish Space Remix)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notebook: &lt;a href="https://github.com/csdurfee/csdurfee.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/nba-clutch-stats.ipynb"&gt;https://github.com/csdurfee/csdurfee.github.io/blob/main/notebooks/nba-clutch-stats.ipynb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I'm discussing &lt;a href="https://www.nba.com/stats/teams/clutch-traditional?Season=2010-11"&gt;team clutch statistics from nba.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A basketball player who tends to make good plays in high-pressure situations is known as being "clutch". When the game is on the line, who do you want taking the last shot, or guarding the other team's best player?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of other psychological phenomena, I think "clutchness" is mostly something we notice in retrospect. It's easy to remember when our favorite players "came up clutch". It's harder to remember times when they didn't, and impossible to accurately decide whether a player is objectively &lt;em&gt;clutcher&lt;/em&gt; than average or not based on our subjective memories, rather than using statistics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;em&gt;hot hand&lt;/em&gt; phenomenon, we notice a player "can't miss" after they've already made a few shots in a row, and then they make another one. Although I've shown that the opposite of the hot hand exists in the NBA, I can't argue against the feeling that a player is &lt;em&gt;on fire&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;can get hot&lt;/em&gt;. I feel it, too. Like &lt;em&gt;clutchness&lt;/em&gt;, some players just seem to have it, and some don't. But I think it's mostly an artifact of how we remember things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps reflected in the NBA's &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NBA_Clutch_Player_of_the_Year"&gt;Clutch Player of the Year award&lt;/a&gt;. Last year, it was won by Jalen Brunson, who is a player I think NBA fans would consider pretty clutch -- at least on offense.  But &lt;a href="https://www.nba.com/stats/players/clutch-traditional?PerMode=Per100Possessions&amp;amp;Season=2024-25&amp;amp;dir=A&amp;amp;sort=AST"&gt;statistically&lt;/a&gt;, besides scoring a lot, Brunson wasn't one of the best players in clutch time last season. His team, the Knicks, only went 17-11 (60.7%) in clutch games, which was almost exactly matched their overall record, 50-32 (61%). They won as many games in the clutch as I'd expect them to. But Brunson feels like a &lt;em&gt;clutch guy&lt;/em&gt;. It's an award based on &lt;em&gt;vibes&lt;/em&gt;, rather than objective facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I'm examining team level NBA clutch statistics. The NBA formally defines &lt;em&gt;clutch time&lt;/em&gt; as the last 5 minutes of a game, when the score is within 5 points. Obviously some threshold had to be chosen, but I wonder if a species with 4 fingers on each hand would have set the threshold at the last 4 minutes, when the game is within 4 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Our old frenemy, conditional probability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The math behind statistics isn't that hard, compared to some kinds (lookin' at you, partial differential equations). The real difficulty is the process of thinking statistically. It's easy to find statistical correlations that seem important or profound, but are actually meaningless once the mess of conditional probabilities are untangled, like a box of old Christmas lights, and the right baseline is established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example I came across recently involves bets on NFL point totals, where one can wager on whether the total number of points scored by both teams is higher or lower than a certain number. Let's say an NFL game is a blowout -- one team wins by more than 20 points. 55% of the time, when a game is a blowout, the bet on the over wins. Is this an interesting correlation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might take the 55% as evidence of the &lt;em&gt;rubber band effect&lt;/em&gt;, where teams that are ahead by a large margin tend to play with less intensity on defense, allowing the other team to score &lt;em&gt;garbage time points&lt;/em&gt; -- scores that don't affect the outcome of the game, but make the final score look more competitive than the game actually was. It looks like the &lt;em&gt;rubber band effect&lt;/em&gt; makes the over point total more likely to win, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nope! There's a hidden conditional. In order for one team to win by at least 20 points, at least one team has to score 20 points first. In the set of games where one team scored at least 20, the over wins 60% of the time. So the game being a blowout lowers the probability of the over winning, when considering those games against their true peers. A 20-0 blowout probably should happen more often than a 40-20 blowout. That makes sense. But so does "teams leading by a lot get lazy on defense, leading to more points than expected". And that's wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Clutch time is mediocrity time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clutch games are pretty common, around half of all NBA contests. That's stayed pretty consistent from year to year, though perhaps the rate is going down over time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="/img/percent-clutch-time.png" src="/img/percent-clutch-time.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a plot of each teams' winning percentage versus percentage of games played in the clutch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="/img/clutch-density.png" src="/img/clutch-density.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order for an NBA game to have clutch time, it has to be a close game in the first place. Really good teams and really bad teams will be involved in fewer &lt;em&gt;clutch&lt;/em&gt; games than teams in the middle, because they're usually either winning or losing by a large margin at the end of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe &lt;em&gt;clutch&lt;/em&gt; should be seen as a backhanded complement. Houston is known as "Clutch City" because of the Rockets, which is an odd thing. For starters, I don't know why a rocket would need a clutch, unless it is some sort of steampunk apparatus. Second, the team that earned the "Clutch City" moniker was the 1993 Rockets, who blew multiple big leads in the Finals, and just barely won the championship in 7 games against a team they should've beaten easily. And it's unlikely the Rockets would have beaten the Bulls, if Michael Jordan hadn't been playing baseball that season. Houston only became "Clutch City" due to luck and the team's inability to finish games off. Is it really &lt;em&gt;clutch&lt;/em&gt; to dig yourself out of a hole that you created? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a similar thing with NFL football. Brett Favre and John Elway are known as clutch quarterbacks because they led a lot of game winning drives. But many times, they were only in the position to have to win the game on the last drive because they threw 3 interceptions earlier in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do especially clutch teams exist?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we should start with the assumption that teams' records in clutch situations should be close to their record overall. Here's a plot of win percentage in clutch vs. non-clutch games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="/img/clutch-non-clutch.png" src="/img/clutch-non-clutch.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams that are bad lose at similar rates in both clutch and non-clutch games. Teams that are good tend to be good in both. Teams that are bad tend to be bad in both. Most teams are mediocre at both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Offense and Defensive Ratings in the clutch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offensive and Defensive Ratings are a measure of the average number of points scored/given up by a team per 100 possessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a clear effect on these numbers in clutch time. Offensive and defensive ratings are both about 2.5 points lower in the final minutes of close games. Either offenses are worse, or defenses are better, or a bit of both. But it's a little bit harder for teams to score.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would constitute evidence that a team actually has a special ability to win games in the clutch, versus just doing what they always do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to look at teams that are better on both offense and defense in clutch situations.  These are the teams in the upper left quadrant of this graph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="/img/clutch-off-def.png" src="/img/clutch-off-def.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I restricted to teams that were at least 3 points better on both offense and defense.  51 teams since 2010 have met that threshold. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That set includes some great teams, such as the 2015 Golden State Warriors, who went a record 73-9 in the regular season, and 3 that won the NBA championship (2010 Mavericks, 2012 Miami Heat, and 2014 Warriors).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the set also includes some truly bad teams, like the 2010 Cleveland Cavaliers, who went 19-63, 2013 Philadelphia 76ers, who also went 19-63, and the 2023 Charlotte Hornets, who went 21-61. 11 of 51 teams on the list didn't even make the playoffs, and 10 of them lost more games than they won.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 40 &lt;em&gt;clutch&lt;/em&gt; teams that made the playoffs won an average of 5.8 playoff games, versus 5.2 for all teams that made the playoffs. So these &lt;em&gt;clutch teams&lt;/em&gt; do a little better in the postseason, but it's not a massive bump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's possible coaching makes a difference. There are four teams coached by Rick Carlisle on the list (2010, 2014, 2015 Mavericks; 2024 Pacers). Or perhaps certain players are significant. There are also four teams starring James Harden (2013, 2017 and 2019 Rockets; 2023 LA Clippers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While being &lt;em&gt;clutch&lt;/em&gt; is a positive signal, but not as strong as being a good team overall. Among the last 15 NBA champions, they average a rank of 5.3 in clutch win percentage, but 2.6 in overall win percentage on the season. Because it's a smaller sample, performance in clutch games really should be a less accurate predictor of team skill than their overall record, and it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on NBA clutch stats next week.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="basketball"></category><category term="basketball"></category></entry><entry><title>Keys to the kingdom</title><link href="/keys-to-the-kingdom.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-12-17T10:20:00-10:00</published><updated>2025-12-17T10:20:00-10:00</updated><author><name>casey durfee</name></author><id>tag:None,2025-12-17:/keys-to-the-kingdom.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Tv0UiQ5n7SM" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="&amp;quot;Pacific State (12&amp;quot; version)&amp;quot;, 808 State" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/Tv0UiQ5n7SM/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Tv0UiQ5n7SM" target="_blank"&gt;"Pacific State (12" version)", 808 State&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Two Georges, damn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the NBA right now, there are two up-and-coming players with very similar names. This seems to keep happening in the league. I wish somebody would do something about it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a few years now, we've had to deal with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Tv0UiQ5n7SM" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="&amp;quot;Pacific State (12&amp;quot; version)&amp;quot;, 808 State" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/Tv0UiQ5n7SM/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Tv0UiQ5n7SM" target="_blank"&gt;"Pacific State (12" version)", 808 State&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Two Georges, damn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the NBA right now, there are two up-and-coming players with very similar names. This seems to keep happening in the league. I wish somebody would do something about it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a few years now, we've had to deal with two players named Jaylin Williams and Jalen Williams who play on the same team and have similarly generic nicknames, forcing hoops fans to remember which one is "J Dub" and which is "Jay Will". This is on top of a dozen other "Jalens" playing for other teams as well. (Do Jalen Rose or his parents get any residuals for all these basketball Jalenses? I hope so.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compounding the problem for Keyonte George of the Utah Jazz and Kyshawn George of the Washington Wizards is the fact they play for two of the worst teams in the league. There's only so much Jazz/Wizards basketball anyone can watch and stay sane, so even avid hoops fans should be forgiven for doing a "Christian Bale"/"Kirsten Bell" thing with them. Even pro sports journalists do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=POcuiqRTbnM" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="&amp;quot;Kristianne Baille&amp;quot; by Trevor Clarence on Youtube" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/POcuiqRTbnM/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both started out looking like they were drowning in the NBA, but they're putting it together, Kyshawn in his second season, Keyonte in his third, so it's time to tune in while you can still say you knew about them before it was cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Kyshawn&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kyshawn George is a floofy haired youth who always looks like he's 15 minutes late to his Political Science class. He should probably be playing in a North Face puffy jacket and pajama pants instead of a Wizards uniform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="/img/kyshawn.jpg" src="/img/kyshawn.jpg"&gt;
All-Pro Reels, CC BY-SA 4.0 &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0"&gt;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&lt;/a&gt;, via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the big hair and the throwback Wizards jersey, he looks a little bit like greatest player in Washington Bullets/Wizards history, Wes Unseld:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="/img/wes-unseld.jpg" src="/img/wes-unseld.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His game is a little Unseld-y, too. Unseld was a 6'7" guy who played center. Guarding much bigger players takes a certain quality -- solidness -- that not all players have. Some guys just occupy space better than others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although he plays small forward, Kyshawn George has that solidness. At his best, Kyshawn just kind of owns the floor, unafraid to bounce off of other players (or go through them) in order to score or get the rebound. And like Unseld, he has good passing skills. If Wes Unseld played today, he might be a point forward like Kyshawn, who is leading the Wizards in assists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At his worst, well, Kyshawn's got a lot to learn. I think he has the capability to be a very good defender, but the Wizards are just awful at defense -- worst in the league by points allowed. It's hard for me to tell how good a player is when they're surrounded by teammates who make lots of defensive mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Keyonte&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keyonte George, looks a bit like, I dunno, Timon from the Lion King. I don't have Timon's scouting report, but Keyonte's a super quick modern point guard who can score as well as set his teammates up. Or at least that was the idea. His first two years in the league were disappointing. He mostly shot 3 pointers, and wasn't especially good at it. As a point guard, he was tentative, and seemed to check out mentally at times when things were going bad (a frequent occurence on the woeful Jazz.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, he's more of an all-around scorer, and much more efficient. He's scoring almost 6 more points per 36 minutes, while only taking 1.7 more shot attempts. A lot of that is driven by getting more free throws -- 3 more made free throws per 36 over last season. He's a threat to score from just about everywhere, after two seasons of not being a threat anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keyonte's still bad on defense. The Jazz are 28th in Defensive Rating, so like Kyshawn, it's awfully hard to say how good he really is when he plays on such a crappy team. His game is similar to DeAaron Fox, who is currently thriving on the Spurs surrounded by significantly above average defenders. So I think he has a bright future even if he never makes a big leap on defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;7'6" man kills giant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shout out to the try-hard Spurs for taking down the Thunder in the NBA cup. The fact that the tallest guy in the NBA took down basketball Goliath is perfect. No notes. My biggest basketball fear is that if the aliens come down and challenge Earth to a game, we're not gonna have anyone who can guard Wemby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mathletix Bajillion, week I guess we're still doing this&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, one of these teams picks randomly, the other algorithmically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ringer went 9-16 on the week, for a 171-204 combined record on the season and 45.6% winning percentage. The mathletix teams didn't cover themselves in glory either, going 3-7. Nobody knows nothin'. All of us are in the gutter, but some of us are staring at the reduced juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lines taken Wednesday afternoon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Neil McAul-Stars&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;last week: 1-4, -321 &lt;br&gt;
Overall: 16-14, +159 &lt;br&gt;
line shopping: +99    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SEA -1.5 -105 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TEN +3 +100 (lowvig)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CAR +3 -106 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NE +3 -108 (lowvig)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ATL -3 +100 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Vincent Hand-Eggs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;last week: 2-3, -110  &lt;br&gt;
Overall: 11-18-1, -781 &lt;br&gt;
line shopping: +99     &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SEA -1.5 -105 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JAX +3 +103 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MIN -3 +109 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LAC +2 +106 (lowvig)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GB +0.5 -110 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="basketball"></category><category term="basketball"></category><category term="bajillion"></category></entry></feed>