<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>mathletix - NBA</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/nba.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2025-11-28T10:20:00-10:00</updated><entry><title>Free throw merchants and the value of stars</title><link href="/free-throw-merchants-and-the-value-of-stars.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-11-28T10:20:00-10:00</published><updated>2025-11-28T10:20:00-10:00</updated><author><name>casey durfee</name></author><id>tag:None,2025-11-28:/free-throw-merchants-and-the-value-of-stars.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qFfnlYbFEiE" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Jimi Hendrix Experience - Voodoo Child (Slight Return) (Live In Maui, 1970)" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/qFfnlYbFEiE/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qFfnlYbFEiE" target="_blank"&gt;The Jimi Hendrix Experience - Voodoo Child (Slight Return) (Live In Maui, 1970)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Jimmy Butler: still good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last season, Jimmy Butler quiet quit on his team. He wanted a new contract from the Miami Heat, and they didn't want to give him one, so he just stopped trying. As a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qFfnlYbFEiE" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Jimi Hendrix Experience - Voodoo Child (Slight Return) (Live In Maui, 1970)" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/qFfnlYbFEiE/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qFfnlYbFEiE" target="_blank"&gt;The Jimi Hendrix Experience - Voodoo Child (Slight Return) (Live In Maui, 1970)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Jimmy Butler: still good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last season, Jimmy Butler quiet quit on his team. He wanted a new contract from the Miami Heat, and they didn't want to give him one, so he just stopped trying. As a fan, it seemed like an annoying and entitled thing to do. He couldn't just play the season out?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Butler eventually ended up getting traded to the Golden State Warriors, who gave him the extension he wanted, and he started trying again. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting aside whether Butler was justified, was the extension worth it or not? Butler is 36 years old, an age where it's totally expected for players to start to decline. The NBA salary cap rules now make it so a team can't afford to get a contract as big as Butler's wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Warriors took a calculated risk, and it paid immediate dividends when Jimmy helped them sneak into the playoffs last year, but the team is about in the same position they were before they got him -- a few high level players, but not in the upper echelon of the league due being old and incomplete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jimmy's doing great, though. He's at career highs in True Shooting (TS%) and effective FG percent (eFG%). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="/img/jimmy-efg.png" src="/img/jimmy-efg.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He's always been an efficient scorer, due to his ability to draw a lot of fouls. That means shooting a lot of free throws, which are easy points. Jimmy has been getting about 2.4x the number of free throws per shot attempt compared to the league average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's about where he's been for several seasons now. His free throw rate saw a huge jump when he moved to the Miami Heat in the 2019-2020 season, and he's maintained that ever since:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="/img/jimmy-ftr.png" src="/img/jimmy-ftr.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The career highs in TS% and eFG% probably aren't sustainable, though. Butler's a career 33% 3 point shooter who's making 45% of them this season. I wouldn't bet on that continuing, but he'll always be valuable on offense if he can draw that many free throws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Butler's defense is still great, as well. The Warriors are 6.5 points per 100 possessions better on defense when he's on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He stands out on all the advanced metrics. Right now, he's 4th in WS/48 (behind Jokic, Shai and Giannis), 8th in PER, 8th in VORP, 3rd in Offensive Rating, 8th in Box Plus/Minus, and 11th in &lt;a href="https://dunksandthrees.com/epm/actual"&gt;EPM&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the numbers he's putting up, I think he's worth the money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ewing theory, 2025 edition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuals don't win games, teams do. Sometimes it can be hard to tell how much of player's individual contribution is actually increasing the likelihood of their team winning. And there's always opportunity cost: perhaps a big man would've been more valuable to this team than Butler has been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a star player gets injured, sometimes a team plays better, a phenomenon Bill Simmons coined "The Ewing Theory". We're seeing some of that this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Atlanta Hawks are 2-3 this season when star Trae Young plays, and 9-4 when he doesn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Memphis Grizzlies are 4-8 when star Ja Morant plays, and 2-4 when he doesn't. (While the win percentage is the same, the team has looked less hapless in those 6 games.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Orlando Magic are 6-6 when star Paolo Banchero plays, and 4-2 when he doesn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three players have distinctive play styles that their team must run to maximize their talents -- to paraphrase James Harden, they are the system. Sometimes maximizing the opportunities for the best player means wasting some of the talents of the other players on the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar distinctive players like Harden, Jokic and Halliburton are far more essential -- their teams are much worse when they are out, despite the same potential on paper for holding their teams back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's the difference between the Hawks, who have been doing better without Trae Young, and the Pacers, who are completely hapless without Tyrese Halliburton? I'm not going to read too much into such small sample sizes, but it's an interesting thing to watch out for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;SGA's FTAs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debates involving subjects anybody can have an opinion about tend to be much louder than subjects requiring specialized knowledge. It's the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_triviality"&gt;law of triviality&lt;/a&gt;. The purest form of this in sports is the question of who is the most valuable player. TThe NBA version of this debate is probably the loudest and least interesting of any sport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are people who don't know much about basketball or statistics, but will argue endlessly on the internet whether BPM or EPM or RAPTOR or VORP is the right metric for deciding who is the best player. Or rather, they decide on the player they like, then find the statistic that says what they want to hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the MVP usually comes down to personal preference -- there are always a handful of players that are clearly better than everybody else, and which one is the most valuable among that set is a matter of taste, and often gets decided by narratives rather than anything rigorous. Perhaps rigor is futile. Pretty much every MVP caliber player is a unique basketball talent. None of them are really interchangeable -- they all break the mold in some way. Any sort of all-in-one number is bound to fail at capturing what makes each one special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps because it is a matter of taste and ultimately a very trivial question, people tend to latch onto style points. Who is funnest to watch, who would be the funnest to play with. Who scores points &lt;em&gt;ethically&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;unethically&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who think that Shai Gilgeous-Alexander (SGA) shouldn't be the MVP derisively call him &lt;em&gt;FTA&lt;/em&gt;, implying he gets awarded more free throws than he deserves, or is otherwise a free throw merchant -- someone who baits defenders into fouling him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shai is currently currently the leader in FTAs this year, so the &lt;em&gt;FTA&lt;/em&gt; nickname is accurate in one sense. Here are the 10 players with the most free throw attempts this season, plus Jokić (15th place.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Attempts&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;FTr&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;FTr+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;PPG&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Shai Gilgeous-Alexander&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;167&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.465&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;164&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;32.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Luka Dončić&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;150&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.551&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;194&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;34.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Deni Avdija&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;143&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.472&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;166&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;24.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Devin Booker&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;141&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.416&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;147&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;26.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;James Harden&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;139&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.488&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;172&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;27.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Franz Wagner&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;136&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.471&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;166&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Giannis Antetokounmpo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;132&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.532&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;188&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;31.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Jimmy Butler&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;132&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.667&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;235&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;19.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Pascal Siakam&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;130&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.444&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;156&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;24.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Tyrese Maxey&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;125&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.334&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;118&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Nikola Jokić&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;116&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;0.395&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;139&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;29.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shai's FTr+ of 164 indicates he gets 1.64x more free throws per shot attempt than the average player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a vacuum, that seems high, but everybody on this list has an FTr+ of over 100. They're all good at drawing fouls. Most high volume scorers are. They score a lot and get fouled a lot for the same reason, they're hard to guard. Jimmy Butler is the king, though -- the only player on the list averaging under 20 points a game, and the only one with an FTr over .600. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jimmy's getting 2 free throws per every 3 shots he attempts. Since he makes 80% of them, that's a free half point Butler gets every time he attempts a shot. As far as free throw merchants go, he's &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_di_Bicci_de%27_Medici"&gt;Giovanni de' Medici&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to his peers, SGA's free throw rate is pretty tame. It's 7th on this list -- lower than Luka Dončić, Deni Avdija, James Harden, Franz Wagner, Giannis, and Jimmy Butler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a little higher than Jokić's, but I don't know how you decide that an FTr+ of 139 is ethical, but an FTr+ of 164 is unethical, or a sign that the refs are in the tank for SGA. So, where's the line? Why do other MVP candidates like Luka and Giannis escape criticism, when they draw more fouls per shot than SGA does?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll take a deeper dive into the topic some other time, but the fact that Luka's free throw rate took a jump when he got traded to the Lakers is another example of why the NBA stands for Not Beating Allegations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mathletix Bajillion, week 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual: one team picks randomly, one team uses a simple algorithm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the mathletix teams have losing records now, but so do all 5 Ringer teams, so it's still anyone's game. We're still saving a lot of (imaginary) money by shopping for lines, instead of taking them at -110. Even though I got lazy with shopping, I still managed to find all 10 bets at reduced juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lines as of Friday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Neil McAul-Stars&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;last week: 1-4, -323
Overall: 7-8, -120
line shopping: +60
* MIA -5.5 -104 (prophetX)
* HOU +3.5 -107 (prophetX)
* WAS +6 -108 (prophetX)
* CAR +10 -108 (prophetX)
* NE -7 +100 (prophetX)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Vincent Hand-Eggs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;last week: 3-2, +97
Overall: 6-8-1, -247
line shopping: +33
* LV +9.5 -104 (lowvig)
* CLE +5 -104 (prophetX)
* PHI -7 -108 (prophetX)
* PIT +3 +100 (lowvig)
* WAS +6 -108 (prophetX)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All data sourced from &lt;a href="https://basketball-reference.com"&gt;basketball-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="NBA"></category><category term="basketball"></category></entry><entry><title>Home of Elvis and the Ancient Greeks</title><link href="/home-of-elvis-and-the-ancient-greeks.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-11-19T10:20:00-10:00</published><updated>2025-11-19T10:20:00-10:00</updated><author><name>casey durfee</name></author><id>tag:None,2025-11-19:/home-of-elvis-and-the-ancient-greeks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bHs_o8qbND0" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="Talking Heads, &amp;quot;Cities&amp;quot;, live at Montreaux Jazz Festival, 1982" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/bHs_o8qbND0/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bHs_o8qbND0" target="_blank"&gt;Talking Heads, "Cities", live at Montreaux Jazz Festival, 1982&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What's going on with the Grizzlies?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest answer is they're miserably bad on offense. It's also the oddest thing about this team to me, since they scored effortlessly last year. The Grizzlies had found something that worked last season …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bHs_o8qbND0" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img alt="Talking Heads, &amp;quot;Cities&amp;quot;, live at Montreaux Jazz Festival, 1982" src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/bHs_o8qbND0/0.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bHs_o8qbND0" target="_blank"&gt;Talking Heads, "Cities", live at Montreaux Jazz Festival, 1982&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What's going on with the Grizzlies?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest answer is they're miserably bad on offense. It's also the oddest thing about this team to me, since they scored effortlessly last year. The Grizzlies had found something that worked last season. They had the 6th best Offensive Rating, and 10th best Defensive Rating.  Considering the Indiana Pacers made it within one game of winning the NBA Championship with the 9th best Offensive Rating and 13th best Defensive Rating, the Grizzlies were definitely a borderline contender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, they're 27th in Offensive Rating, 21 positions worse than last year. (The falloff on defense is a little more understandable, since they have several very good defensive players injured right now.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eFG+ is a measure of effective FG%, normalized so that 100 is league average.  Here are the top 8 Grizzlies players by minutes played the last two seasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;Position&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;2025&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left;"&gt;2024&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;2025 eFG+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;2024 eFG+&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right;"&gt;Diff&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Center&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Jock Landale&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Zach Edey&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;108&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;111&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;-3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;PF&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Jaren Jackson Jr&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Jaren Jackson Jr&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;98&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;101&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;-3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;SF&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Jaylen Wells&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Jaylen Wells&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;82&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;97&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;-15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;SG&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;KCP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Desmond Bane&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;77&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;104&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;-27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;PG&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Ja Morant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Ja Morant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;93&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;-22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Bench 1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Santi Aldama&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Santi Aldama&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;96&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;106&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;-10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Bench 2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Cedric Coward&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Scottie Pippen Jr&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;102&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Bench 3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Cam Spencer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left;"&gt;Brandon Clarke&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;109&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;115&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right;"&gt;-6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except for rookie Cedric Coward, every single slot is a downgrade. Wells and Aldama have been significantly worse than last season, but the most dramatic is Ja Morant. The only player with around as many minutes played and a lower eFG+ are &lt;a href="https://www.basketball-reference.com/players/s/sheppbe01.html"&gt;Ben Sheppard&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.basketball-reference.com/players/w/walkeja02.html"&gt;Jarace Walker&lt;/a&gt; of the Indiana Pacers, young players who have been forced into playing a lot of minutes due to injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where have all the backup PGs gone?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big problem for the Grizzlies is that they don't really have a backup point guard. They're far from the only team with a lack of PGs on the roster this season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dallas Mavericks have been playing rookie forward Cooper Flagg as PG even though they knew their starting PG, Kyrie Irving, was injured coming into the season. The Nuggets have been experimenting with having forward Peyton Watson as backup PG. The Houston Rockets have no true PG in their "oops, all bigs" starting lineup, though Reed Sheppard is playing more and more off the bench, and looking pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's an odd trend to me. Backup point guards have traditionally been cheap and easy to find -- guys like Ish Smith and D.J Augustin. They're like small, functional trucks. They made a ton of them back in the day, but they kinda don't exist anymore, despite how useful and reasonably priced they were. Does that make &lt;a href="https://www.basketball-reference.com/players/k/kawamyu01.html"&gt;Yuki Kawamura&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kei_truck"&gt;Kei truck&lt;/a&gt; of this analogy? Yes, yes it does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rockets and Nuggets are doing fine so far without playing a backup PG, but the Grizzlies' situation is just baffling to me. Ja Morant is one of the more injury prone players in the league. You didn't think you needed to find a real backup for him? (Wouldn't Russell Westbrook look good in a Grizzlies uniform?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Grizzlies have a stretch of easier opponents coming up, so I think they'll start looking a little better for that reason alone. Maybe they'll get some mojo back. But I'm always about process, rather than outcomes, and I just don't get the Grizzlies' process right now. They had something pretty cool going last year, and now they don't. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams can't control a lot of factors. Injuries, who they play on a given night, the bounce of the ball on the rim on a last second shot. There's a lot of luck. But the Grizzlies' problems seem to come down to things the coaching staff and front office can control: vision, planning, vibes, communication, style of play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Mathletix Bajillion, week 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these teams is random, one is chosen by an algorithm put together by me, a non-football guy. Can you guess which one is which?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All lines are as of Thursday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Neil McAul-Stars&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;last week: 1-4, -301  &lt;br&gt;
Overall: 6-4, +203  &lt;br&gt;
line shopping: +43    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PIT +2.5 -105 (lowvig)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GB -6.5 +100 (lowvig)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NO -2 -108 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TB +6.5 +101 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHI -3 -110 (hard rock)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Vincent Hand-Eggs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;last week: 2-2-1, -10  &lt;br&gt;
Overall: 3-6-1, -344  &lt;br&gt;
line shopping: +16    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CIN +6.5 -107 (rivers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CHI -2.5 -105 (lowvig)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ATL +2 -102 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BUF -5.5 -101 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DET -10.5 -102 (prophetx)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="NBA"></category><category term="basketball"></category><category term="bajillion"></category></entry></feed>